A Guide to the David Rockefeller Personal and Professional papers, RG 1 and RG 2 FA436
Rockefeller Archive Center
David Rockefeller Personal and Professional papers, RG 1 and RG 2
1918-1985
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, David (1915-2017)
Rockefeller, Peggy
FA436
21.22 Cubic Feet 51 letter document boxes 1 record storage box Audiovisual materials
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
As received.
- Audiovisual materials, 1941-2015; 1; 2.99 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research. When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  All inquiries to view films require advanced notice of at least 2 business days, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those that are not available in modern formats, may be restricted at the discretion of RAC.
  Moving Images
  - Film, 1959-1978; 1
    - Chase Manhattan Bank: New Building Progress Report, 1959; Silent, Color, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1064)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Open for research. Access copy available (silent). Access copy with sound currently unavailable. Please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
      Scope and Contents note
      Publicity film produced by Chase Manhattan Bank about their new headquarters in Lower Manhattan.
    - David Rockefeller- Dresden Exhibition, 1978 October 18; Silent, Color, 1 minute; 16mm film (Reel AV 1604)
      Open for research. Digital access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
      David Rockefeller at opening of Metropolitan Museum of Art exhibition.
    - David Rockefeller Trip to Ivory Coast, 1971 November; Silent, Black and white, 52 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1724)
      Footage from trip.
  - Video recordings, 1941-2015; 2; 2.99 Cubic Feet
    - Public Account with David Rockefeller, 1983 October 25; Sound, Color, 9 minutes; Betamax (Box 1, Tape AV 11123)
      Open for research. Digital access copy available.
      Scope and Contents
      Interview on BBC Scotland television program.
    - Rockefeller Family Celebration for Laurance S. Rockefeller's 90th Birthday and David Rockefeller's 85th Birthday, 2000 June 17; Sound, Color, 79 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11124)
      Event documentation.
    - David Rockefeller on Charlie Rose Show, 1998 December 01; Sound, Color, 55 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11125)
      Interview
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Poor image quality
    - David Rockefeller on Charlie Rose Show, 2002 October 22; Sound, Color, 39 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11126)
      Conversation with David Rockefeller regarding the publication of his memoir.
    - David Rockefeller and David Rockefeller Jr on CNN International Hour, 2015 October 28; Sound, Color, 14 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11127)
      Interview regarding passing the leadership of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to David Rockefeller Jr.
    - David Rockefeller Visits Opening of Museum of Modern Art Touring Exhibition in Japan, circa1993; Sound, Color, 7 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11128)
      Event documentation on Japanese television program.
    - David Rockefeller and the Announcement of the Recipients of The Praemium Imperiale, 1989 September 15; Sound, Color, 16 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11129)
      Event documentation from New York.
    - David Rockefeller on the Today Show, 2002 October 22; Sound, Color, 6 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11130)
      Interview: Katie Couric and David Rockefeller on his recently published memoir.
    - David Rockefeller on Face the Nation, circa1987; Sound, Color, 9 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11131)
      Interview discussing the Black Monday stock market crash and the country's financial recovery.
    - David Rockefeller on Eye Witness News: Rainbow Room Reopening, circa 2014; Sound, Color, 6 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11132)
      Multiple news reports on the Rainbow Room reopening.
    - David Rockefeller at Paul Robeson High School - Live at 5, 5 pm Broadcast, circa 1985; Sound, Color, 4 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11133)
      David Rockefeller speaks with New York City 9th grade students.
    - David Rockefeller at Paul Robeson High School - Live at 5, 6 pm Broadcast, circa 1985; Sound, Color, 4 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11134)
      David Rockefeller speaks with New York City 9th graders about values.
    - David Rockefeller at Senator Jacob K. Javits Funeral (News 9), 1986; Sound, Color, 5 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11135)
      Event documentation on News 9.
      Mediocre image and sound quality.
    - David Rockefeller Interview on the Trilateral Commission, May 1986; Sound, Color, 10 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11138)
    - David Rockefeller Discusses the Americas Society on the Today Show, 1987 June 02; Sound, Color, 6 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11139)
      David Rockefeller and Marife Hernandez discuss the Americas Society.
    - David Rockefeller on Meet the Press, 1963 March 3; Sound, Black and white, 34 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11140)
      Panel discussion of President John F. Kennedy's budget proposal for 1964 (David Rockefeller, President of Chase Manhattan Bank)
      Burnt-in timecode
    - David Rockefeller Press Conference and News Coverage Regarding Mitsubishi Buying a Major Share of Rockefeller Center, circa1989; Sound, Color, 75 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11141)
      Press events and new coverage of Mitsubishi Estate Company taking control of Rockefeller Center.
      Various quality; some clips have low volume and poor image quality.
    - A Birthday Celebration for David Rockefeller and Laurance S. Rockefeller at Pocantico Hills, 1990 June 15; Sound, Color, 92 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11142)
      Event documentation, including speeches.
      Intermittent low volume
    - David Rockefeller and David Rockefeller Jr. on the Today Show, 1987 October 27; Sound, Color, 6 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11143)
      Interview with Bryant Gumble regarding David Rockefeller Jr. taking over leadership of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund.
    - Interview with Mr. and Mrs. David Rockefeller, 1995 October 15; Sound, Color, 31 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11144)
      Discussion about the restoration of Colonial Williamsburg, the Rockefellers' involvement with the African American community, the Folk Art Center, among other topics. David speaks about his parents' influence on his life. Peggy recalls her memories of JDR Jr. and Abby Rockefeller.
    - David Rockefeller: Bridge Builder (A Tribute), 2003 September 06; Sound, Color, 13 minutes; VHS (Box 1, Tape AV 11146)
      The Synergos Institute tribute video featuring Peggy Dulany, Richard Parsons, Kofi Annan, Peter G. Peterson, Maria Elena Lagomasino, Neil Rudenstine, Gordon Conway, John M. Forgach, Kathryn S. Wylde, Glenn Lowry, and S. Bruce Schearer. Produced, Directed, and Written by Roger Torda.
    - Stars Among the World Leaders: Interview with David Rockefeller, 1982 March; Umatic (Box 2, Tape AV 13027)
      Interview by Mrs. Kaoru Nakamaru, Executive Producer TV Series: "Stars Among the World's Leaders"
    - UP CLOSE with David Rockefeller, Umatic; 30 minutes (Box 20, Tape AV 13028)
    - Today Show - David Rockefeller, 1981 August 5; Umatic (Box 21, Tape AV 13029)
      WNBC-TV, NBC Network, Wednesday, 9:00 AM
    - Message For Peace with David Rockefeller, Umatic (Box 22, Tape AV 13030)
      WNBC-TV, NBC Network, NBC Nightly News, June 12, Saturday, 6:30PM
- Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller, 1918-1981; 1945-1961; 2; 19.37 Cubic Feet 51 letter document boxes
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  These records were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by David Rockefeller, August 1987.
  Record Group 2 of the David Rockefeller Papers contains his personal files dated 1918 to 1961 from the Rockefeller family office, known as the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR). The office was located in Rockefeller Center on the 56th floor of the main building at 30 Rockefeller Plaza, contemporaneously referred to as the RCA Building.
  Mr. Rockefeller's personal files begin with his formative years and education, documenting his early interest in science and his family's extensive travels. But the focus of this record group is the 15 years following his service during World War II in the U.S. Army, when David Rockefeller was establishing himself in the arenas of banking, international business, and philanthropy. While his personal and philanthropic activities are well represented in the files, the business records of his 35-year career with Chase Bank are not part of this collection.
  The largest portion of this record group comprises 21 boxes of personal correspondence that date from the immediate post-war period until 1961. Mostly unsolicited, these letters come from friends and acquaintances from across the globe and amply illustrate the vast range of relationships he cultivated through the years. Mr. Rockefeller often heard from individuals he met during his wartime service in France and Algiers—which was, in his own words, "the beginning of a networking process that I would follow throughout my life."* Correspondents of note include Alfred Barr, Jr., Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands, Allen and John Foster Dulles, President Dwight D. Eisenhower, Dag Hammarskjold, General George C. Marshall, Robert Moses, Arthur Sulzberger, and William Zorach.
  Personal correspondence with his parents, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, dates from 1925 until his graduation from Harvard University in 1936, and later with solely his father following Abby's death in 1948. While there are a handful of files related to David Rockefeller's wedding to Margaret McGrath and their honeymoon in Wyoming, there is no correspondence between the two prior to their marriage in 1940. Likewise, there is little to no correspondence with his sister and four brothers. Correspondence regarding his children remains closed to research during their respective lifetimes.
  Among topics of note in this record group is David Rockefeller's close association with Harvard University that spans several decades. This includes folders on his financial support of the institution, as well as his lengthy service on its Board of Overseers. Additionally, folders on his 25th class reunion in 1961—for which he was elected Chief Marshall of the event—are complemented by details of his efforts to mount a special art exhibition for the occasion. Other aspects of his lifelong love of art are evident in the folders on the Museum of Modern Art, which his mother co-founded and on whose board Mr. Rockefeller served starting in 1948. Furthermore, information on the origins of his own art collecting is found in Folders 210-217.
  From a young age, David Rockefeller fully embraced his family's tradition of extensive travel. His 1932 handwritten accounts of a biking trip in England before starting college detailed the summer adventure in letters home to his parents (Folder 437). In 1935, he toured dozens of European art museums with close friend Richard Gilder, his Harvard roommate who later died while serving as a combat pilot in World War II. During that trip, Richard wrote a particularly poignant letter to Abby Rockefeller that describes their summer travels through Europe and focuses on the ominous developments in Germany as the continent headed toward war (Folder 441).
  Lastly, this record group includes personal and quasi-professional files from 1959 to 1981 that the Chase Manhattan Bank transferred to the family office following David Rockefeller's retirement in 1981. These are mostly chronological, event-specific folders.
  * Rockefeller, David, Memoirs, New York: Random House, 2002, page 122.
  The files were arranged by the Rockefeller family archivist, Joseph Ernst, and much of the original order has been maintained. However, on occasion, files have been rearranged to reflect a more logical order and a folder title has been adjusted to better reflect its contents. For the most part, they follow an alphabetical run of subject areas, followed by correspondence with family members, and then the lengthy run of post-war personal correspondence that is arranged alphabetically by last name.
  Open for research, except where specific restrictions are noted.
  Material in the Rockefeller family collections that details correspondence with or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family member, is restricted from access. Additionally, some records are restricted to safeguard personal privacy.
  - General correspondence
    - 1918-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1939-1944 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
      Restricted material
    - 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
    - 1960-1961 August (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1961 September-1961 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Apartment (115 East 67th Street), 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Lease arrangements
    - Army service, 1942-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Training. Article on Army Reserves.
    - Awards, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Honorary degrees and medals. LIst of awards and citations received.
    - Biography and activities, 1951-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Copies of prepared biographical statements and published articles on DR
    - Biography and activities, 1951-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13a)
    - Birth certificate and affidavit, 1915, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Karl S. Cate, 1945-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      American business man in France, active in political life. DR contribution.
    - College expenses, 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      JDR Jr. cautious about extravagance. Tuition, room and board.
    - Insurance, 1940-1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Jewelry coverage
    - Loans, 1941-1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Personal loan to R. W. Gilder. Business loan to C. A. Kinard.
    - Miami, Florida house, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Adjustments of rent
    - Pocantico Hills house (Stevens House), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      JDR Jr. help in furnishing house.
  - Aldrich family correspondence, 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Brothers and sisters of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. DR's uncles and aunts: Alexander; Edward; Nelson W.; Nelson W. Jr.; Richard and his wife, Daisy; William.
  - Aldrich family correspondence, 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21a)
    Restricted material. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from access
  - Lucy Aldrich correspondence, 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    DR's aunt. Correspondence. Death. Settling of estate.
  - Lucy Aldrich correspondence, 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 22a)
  - Winthrop Aldrich correspondence, 1946-1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    DR's uncle and his wife, Harriet. Correspondence.
  - Articles, 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Articles by and about DR. DR wrote articles for "General Electric Quarterly" and "Iron Age."
  - Benevolences, 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    History of DR and Mrs. DR's giving.
  - Boats
    - Bull's eye "Tar Baby", 1955 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Bull's eye "Tar Baby", 1955 (Box 3, Folder 26a)
    - Sloop "Jack Tar", 1946-1954 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - International sloop "Maine Star" (formerly "Tartar"), 1949-1958 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Luders sloop "Shooting Star", 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Luders sloop "Shooting Star", 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 29a)
    - Power cruiser "Tartan", 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Ketch yacht "Wayfarer", 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Ketch yacht "Wayfarer", 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Business
    - American Anglo-Transvaal Investment Corporation Ltd., 1946-1951 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Investment in African mining venture
    - Chateau Lascombes, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Investment in vineyards in France. Receiving wines. DR gifts of wines. Wishes to liqudate interests.
    - Equitable Life Assurance Society, 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      On Board of Directors and serves on various committees.
    - Fazenda Bodoquena, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Interest in Brazilian ranch
    - Filtisaf, 1946-1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Interest in Congo textile firm
    - Fort Worth industrial development, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      DR approval of Rockefeller Center, Inc.; investment in real estate venture.
    - B. F. Goodrich Company, 1954-1961 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      On Board of Directors. Gift matching program to aid education scholarship fund. Committee to recommend auditors. Money received for directorship.
    - B. F. Goodrich Company, 1954-1961 (Box 3, Folder 39a)
      Restricted material - personal & confidential.
    - International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) and IBEC Research Institute (IRI), 1947-1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      Investments. DR an IRI trustee. Served as IRI president in NAR's absence.
    - Laboratory for Electronics, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Contractors for airborne navigation equipment. On Board of Directors; resignation from board.
    - Pierre Cheyne, Inc., 1946-1961 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      DR's investment in restaurant on Madison Avenue, La Valois. Sold out. DR personal interest in Pierre Cheyne. Changes in personal relationship over years. Pierre Cheyne's work in Chase Bank.
    - Punta Alegre Sugar Corporation, 1951-1959 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      DR a director.
    - Rockefeller Center, Inc., 1946-1961 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      DR a stockholder. North property. Recapitalization of Rockefeller Center. Rockefeller Center gifts.
    - Tanganyika Concessions Ltd., 1951 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      Rockefeller Center investments in African mining venture.
    - Westchester County bank/National Bank of Westchester, 1953-1957 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Merger of county banks into National Bank of Westchester. Infusion of Rockefeller money.
  - Civic
    - American Legion, Chase national Bank post, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      Nominal member. Contributions.
    - Business Advisory Council, 1950-1953 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Member of Council and Committee on Latin America. Studies of Latin American problems.
    - Chamber of Commerce of New York State, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      Housing problems
    - International Chamber of Commerce, U.S. Council, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      On board of trustees
    - Citizens Non-Partisan Committee, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Member
    - Civil Defense, New York City Office, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      Member of advisory comittee in New York City
    - LaGuardia committees: Civil defense uniform, memorial association, 1945-1958 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      Contributions
    - Lower Manhattan development, 1957, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      Downtown Manhattan Association, Inc. DR on board of directors. List of members.
    - Lower Manhattan development, 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Mayor's Advisory Committee, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      Membership working with New York Mayor Robert Wagner
    - New York City 300th anniversary celebration, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 57)
      Contributions. On boad of directors of comittee.
    - Regional Plan Association, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 58)
      DR's address to association on metropolitan transportation.
    - Republican Campaign for Maine, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 59)
      DR led effort to get campaign contributions from summer residents. Discussion of Richard Nixon.
    - Bronx Commuter Terminal, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 60)
      Study of commutation problems
    - Westchester County Planning Commission, 1947-1959 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      Member. Transporation problems.
  - Clubs
    - General summary, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Capitol Hill Club, Washington, DC, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Century Association, Manhattan, 1945-1961 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Chicago Club, Chicago, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Clifton Dock Corporation, Northeast Harbor, Maine, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - 13 West 54th Street Club, Manhattan, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - D.U. Club Corporation, Massachusetts, 1946-1960 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Ekwanok Country Club, Manchester, Vermont, 1958, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Economic Club of New York, Manhattan, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Fifth Avenue Club, Manhattan, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Harbor Club, Seal Harbor, Maine, 1953-1961 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Harbor Club cottages, Seal Harbor, Maine, 1955-1960 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Harbor Club tennis, Seal Harbor, Maine, 1951-1953 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Harvard Club of New York City, 1945-1960 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Historical Society of the Tarrytowns, Tarrytown, New York, 1946-1961 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Kebo Valley Club, Bar Harbor, Maine, 1953-1955 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Knickerbocker Club, Manhattan, 1950-1959 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - The Links, Manhattan, 1948-1957 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Lucullus Circle, Manhattan, 1953-1959 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Northeast Harbor Fleet, Northeast Harbor, Maine, 1952-1961 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Northeast Harbor Fleet, Northeast Harbor, Maine, 1952-1961 (Box 6, Folder 81a)
    - The Moorings, Southwest Harbor, Maine, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Pilgrims of the United States, Manhattan, 1946-1957 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Pot and Kettle, Bar Harbor, Maine, 1956-1961 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - The Recess Club, Manhattan, 1948-1961 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Rockefeller Center Luncheon Club, Manhattan, 1955, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Signet Society, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1953-1960 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Sleepy Hollow Country Club, Scarborough, New York, 1947-1961 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - St. George's Society of New York, Manhattan, 1952-1957 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Tavern Club, Boston, Massachusetts, 1951-1960 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Thursday Evening Club, Manhattan, 1950-1958 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - University Club, Manhattan, 1945-1960 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - University Club, Manhattan, 1945-1960 (Box 7, Folder 92a)
  - Contributions
    - 1935-1949 (Box 7, Folder 93)
      National Catholic Rural Life Conference of the United States. Robert M. Strozier Fund. Mt. Desert Recreation. International Development Services, Inc. British Apprentice Club. U.S. Chamber of Commerce. Boys Club Foundation of Boston, etc.
    - 1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Cultural
    - American Museum of Natural History, 1946-1958 (Box 7, Folder 97)
      DR contributions. Studies of DR's beetle collection. Additions. Gifts to museum of portions of DR's insect collections.